Michael Bourdeaux papers, Inclusive: 1958-2020, undated, Bulk: 1965-1996, undated
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Michael Bourdeaux papers
Inclusive: 1958-2020, undated, Bulk: 1965-1996, undated
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
24
Bourdeaux, Michael Allen, 1934 -
23 A4 document boxes
The Michael Bourdeaux Papers contain materials produced or collected by Rev. Canon Dr. Michael Bourdeaux, founder of Keston College in the United Kingdom.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Michael Bourdeaux was born in 1934 in in the Cornish village of Praze-an-Beeble in England. After attending Truro School, he studied Russian as training for his National Service. He spent five years at St. Edmund Hall, Oxford University, reading Modern Languages and then Theology.
A decisive moment in his life occurred in 1959, when the British Council selected him to the first-ever exchange program with the Soviet Union. During his year at Moscow University, persecution of religion recommenced under Nikita Khrushchev. Thereafter, he devoted his life to making known to the larger world what was happening in the Soviet Union and the Warsaw Pact countries.
After ordination in the Church of England, Michael Bourdeaux, with support from others, founded in 1969 the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the name changed to Keston College in 1974. Keston collected and publicized details about religious persecution and church-state relations behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.”
Bourdeaux’s work highlighted the survival and later revival of religion during these years. At one time, Keston College employed 25 people, established the Keston News Service, produced more than 30 books, and published the journal, Religion in Communist Lands. Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist and totalitarian countries.
In 1984, Michael Bourdeaux received the Templeton Prize for Progress in Religion. He became an honorary canon of Rochester in 1989, and in 1996, the Archbishop of Canterbury awarded him a Lambeth Doctorate of Divinity. He officially retired in 1999 but has continued a worldwide program of lecturing and writing and remains an active member of the Keston Council. His completed memoirs, One Word of Truth: The Cold War Memoir of Michael Bourdeaux and Keston College, was published in 2019 in London by Darton, Longman, and Todd.
After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University where they are housed in the Michael Bourdeaux Research Center and include numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals as well as Keston College archives and papers of its founder and staff.
Scope and Content
The Michael Bourdeaux Papers consist of manuscripts, publications, radio broadcasts, lecture notes, interviews, obituaries, research notes, financial receipts, legal contracts, reports, newspaper and magazine clippings, printed materials, and correspondence.
The materials cover a period from 1958 to 2020 with the bulk from 1965 to 1996. The majority of the collection is related to Michael Bourdeaux’s literary productions, including manuscripts of his books, printed copies of his articles, copies of his lectures, and letters with his publishers. Other significant topics include the reception of the Templeton Prize, the founding of Keston College, and proselytism in Russia.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received the Michael Bourdeaux Papers organized into the following series: Correspondence, Writings, and Templeton Foundation Materials. The original filing system has been preserved when possible, but the collection has also been subdivided into more specific thematic and chronological units.
The Michael Bourdeaux Papers are currently divided into three series: I. Correspondence; II. Literary Works; and III. Templeton Foundation Materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 24.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Bourdeaux, Michael Allen, 1934-
Subjects (Organizations)
British Broadcasting Corporation.; Keston Institute.; RFE/RL.; World Council of Churches.
Places
Europe -- History.; Soviet Union -- Church history.
Subjects
Book reviews.; Christians -- Russia.; Christians -- Soviet Union.; Church and state -- Soviet Union -- History.; Communism and Christianity -- Soviet Union -- History.; Financial records.; Freedom of expression.; Freedom of religion -- Soviet Union — History.; Freedom of the press.; Human rights.; Interviews.; Lecture notes.; Lectures.; Obituaries.; Persecution -- Soviet Union -- History.; Radio scripts.; Radio stations.; Television broadcasting -- Great Britain.; Templeton Foundation Prize.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Manuscripts.
- Correspondence, 1960-2016, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Biography/Profile
  The Correspondence Series includes incoming and outgoing letters primarily related to Michael Bourdeaux’s publications, but also including letters with members of the Keston staff, and other individuals. The series is in good condition.
  - Correspondence: General, 1961-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: General, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: General, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: General, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: General, 1986-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: General, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: General, 1992 January-June (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: General, 1992 July-December (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: General, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: General, 1994 January-June (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: General, 1994 July-December (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: General, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: General, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: General, 1998 January-July (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: General, 1998 August-December (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: General, 2001-2008 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: General, 2015-2018 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: General, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing: General, 1984 January (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing: General, 1984 February (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing: General, 1984 March (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing: General, 1984 April (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing: General, 1984 May (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing: General, 1984 June (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing: General, 1984 July (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing: General, 1984 August (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing: General, 1984 September (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing: General, 1984 October (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing: General, 1984 November (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing: General, 1984 December (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing: General, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing (A-B), 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing (C-D), 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing (E-G), 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing (H-K), 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing (L-M), 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing (N-Q), 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing (R-S), 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing (T-W), 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing (X-Z), 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: “The Lutheran”, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: “The Catholic Herald”, 1966-1975 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: “The Sunday Times”, 1966-1986 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: “The Christian Times”, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: “Common Cause”, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: “Eastern Churches Review”, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: “The Christian Science Monitor”, 1970-1975 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: “Slavonic and East European Review”, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Pertaining to Yuri Titov, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: “The Times Literary Supplement”, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: “The Life of Faith”, 1971-1976 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: “The Methodist Recorder”, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: “Soviet Studies”, 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Various Publishers, 1962-1992 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: “Radio Liberty” (1 of 3), 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: “Radio Liberty” (2 of 3), 1971 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: “Radio Liberty” (3 of 3), 1972-1974, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: “BBC”, 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: “Minority Rights Group” (1 of 2), 1970-1975 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: “Minority Rights Group” (2 of 2), 1976 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence: “World Christian Handbook”, 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence: Pertaining to Doctor of Divinity Degree, 1976-1981 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence: Pertaining to Luce Professorship at Occidental College, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Pertaining to Trip to Australia: Keston College (Vic.), 1982 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Pertaining to Billy Graham's Interview with USA Today, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Republican Policy Committee, United States Senate, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Svetlana Allilueva: "An Icon of Annunciation", 1990 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Margaret Thatcher, 1991 February (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Mark Eliott: Institute for East West Christian Studies, 1991-1993 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Raymond Oppenheim: Keston College New Zealand, 1991-1995 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: James Wood: International Academy for Freedom of Religion and Belief, 1991-1993 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: James Wood: Journal of Church and State, 1991-1993 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Derek Davis: Journal of Church and State, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Pertaining to "Report on the Visit to the Patriarchate of Moscow" by Brian Regan, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Speaking Engagement Invitations, 1992-1995 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Canon W. J. Milligan, Anglican Representative at the European Institutions and Chaplain In Strasbourg, 1993-1995 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Pertaining to Return of Icons to Solovki Monastery, 1993-2001 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Retirement Announcement Letters, 1997-1998 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Wheaton College: Deyneka Collection, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Peter Deyneka Russian Ministries, 1991, 2000, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Consultation on World Evangelization (COWE) Report, Thailand, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Konrad Veem, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Michael Thwaites, 1987, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Literary Works, 1958-2019, undated; 2
  The Literary Works Series includes all those materials written, edited, or co-authored by Michael Bourdeaux. The types of documents in this series include manuscripts, clippings, and related correspondence. The series is in good condition.
  - Book: Opium of the People: Loose-leaf copy with handwritten edits, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Book: Opium of the People: First Draft: "Christianity In the Soviet Union Today", Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Book: Opium of the People: Notes for Further Reading, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Book: Opium of the People: Correspondence Pertaining to Domestic Publication, 1964-1970 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Book: Opium of the People: Correspondence Pertaining to Foreign Publication, 1965-1970 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Book: Opium of the People: Correspondence: Personal Inquiries and Congratulations, 1965-1970 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Book: Opium of the People: Reviews, 1965-1967 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Book: Opium of the People: Financial Documents: Receipts, order forms, royalty notices, 1965-1969 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Book: Opium of the People: BBC Broadcast: Scripts, clippings and correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Book: Opium of the People: Agreement with Faber and Faber Limited, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Book: Opium of the People: BBC Broadcast: Scripts, clippings and correspondence, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Book: Aida of Leningrad: Manuscript of the Trial and Aida's Defense Speech with handwritten notes, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Book: Aida of Leningrad: Correspondence Pertaining to Publication, 1971-1976 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Book: Aida of Leningrad: Reviews, 1972-1976 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Book: Patriarch and Prophets: Correspondence Pertaining to Publications, 1968-1972 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Book: Patriarch and Prophets: Correspondence Pertaining to Translation, 1968-1970 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Book: Patriarch and Prophets: Reviews, 1970-1976 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Book: Patriarch and Prophets: Review Lists, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Book: Patriarch and Prophets: Order forms, receipts, cover design, and financial Information, 1970, 1976, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Book: Faith on Trial in Russia: Chapters 1-3: Draft Manuscript (1 of 3), 1970 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Book: Faith on Trial in Russia: Chapters 1-3: Draft Manuscript (2 of 3), 1971 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Book: Faith on Trial in Russia: Chapters 1-3: Draft Manuscript (3 of 3), 1971 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Book: Faith on Trial in Russia: Chapters 4-5: Draft Manuscript (1 of 3), 1970 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Book: Faith on Trial in Russia: Chapters 4-5: Draft Manuscript (2 of 3), 1971 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Book: Faith on Trial in Russia: Chapters 4-5: Draft Manuscript (3 of 3), 1971 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Book: Faith on Trial in Russia: Chapters 6-7: Draft Manuscript (1 of 2), 1970 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Book: Faith on Trial in Russia: Chapters 6-7: Draft Manuscript (2 of 2), 1971 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Book: Faith on Trial in Russia: Chapter 7: Draft Manuscript, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Book: Faith on Trial in Russia: Correspondence Pertaining to Domestic Publication, 1969-1975 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Book: Faith on Trial in Russia: Correspondence Pertaining to Foreign Publication, 1969-1975 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Book: Faith on Trial in Russia: Reviews, 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Book: Russian Christians on Trial: Korean Translation, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Book: White Book on Restrictions of Religion In the USSR, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Book: White Book on Restrictions of Religion In the USSR: Spare, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Book: White Book on Restrictions of Religion In the USSR: Amended Version, 1975 April (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Book: White Book on Restrictions of Religion In the USSR: Correspondence Pertaining to Publication, 1973-1976 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Preface, Chapter 1 "The First Soviet Invasion: A Foretaste of Persecution": Manuscript, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Chapter 2 "Basic Aims of German and Soviet Policy": Manuscript, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Chapter 3 "Kremlin or Vatican Rule?": Manuscript, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Chapter 4 "The Central Issues": Manuscript, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Chapter 5 "The Central Conflict": Manuscript, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Chapter 6 "The Theological Seminary of Kaunas": Manuscript, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Chapter 7 "The Churches": Manuscript, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Chapter 8 "The Faith of the People": Manuscript, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Chapter 9 "The Battle for the Minds of the Young": Manuscript, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Chapter 10 "Christian Publications": Manuscript, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Chapter 11 "Case 345": Manuscript, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Chapter 12 "Religion, Nationalism, and Human Rights": Manuscript, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Correspondence Pertaining to Domestic Publication, 1977-1979 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Correspondence Pertaining to Foreign Publication (1 of 2), 1977-1979 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Correspondence Pertaining to Foreign Publication (2 of 2), 1979-1981 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Correspondence with Eppstein, John and Sapiets, Marite, 1980-1981 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Correspondence: Contact Information and Addresses of Publishers, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Correspondence: Proofs and Outlines to Send to Publishers, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Contract with Augustine Publishing Company, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Book: Land of Crosses: Reviews, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Book: God's Anvil: John Eppstein's Manuscript (1 of 2), 1982 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Book: God's Anvil: John Eppstein's Manuscript (2 of 2), 1982 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Book: God's Anvil: Draft Manuscript (1 of 4), 1982 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Book: God's Anvil: Draft Manuscript (2 of 4), 1982 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Book: God's Anvil: Draft Manuscript (3 of 4), 1982 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Book: God's Anvil: Draft Manuscript (4 of 4), 1982 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Book: God's Anvil: Manuscript: pp. 1-55, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Book: God's Anvil: Manuscript: pp. 56-106, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Book: God's Anvil: Notes and References, 1982, undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Book: Gorbachev, Glasnost, and the Gospel: Acknowledgments, Postscript, Chapter 1 "The Crisis of History": Draft Manuscript, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Book: Gorbachev, Glasnost, and the Gospel: Chapter 2 "Gorbachev and His Times": Draft Manuscript 1, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Book: Gorbachev, Glasnost, and the Gospel: Chapter 2 "Gorbachev and His Times": Draft Manuscript 2, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Book: Gorbachev, Glasnost, and the Gospel: Chapter 3 "Orthodox Millennium": Draft Manuscript, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Book: Gorbachev, Glasnost, and the Gospel: Chapter 4 "New Law and Old Institutions": Draft Manuscript, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Book: Gorbachev, Glasnost, and the Gospel: Chapter 5 "The Orthodox Church and the People": Draft Manuscript, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Book: Gorbachev, Glasnost, and the Gospel: Chapter 6 "The Protestants": Draft Manuscript, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Book: Gorbachev, Glasnost, and the Gospel: Chapter 7 "The Baltic on Fire": Draft Manuscript, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Book: Gorbachev, Glasnost, and the Gospel: Chapter 8 "Ukrainian Catholics: Tragedy to Triumph": Draft Manuscript, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Book: Gorbachev, Glasnost, and the Gospel: Chapter 9 "The Quality of Mercy", 1990 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Book: Gorbachev, Glasnost, and the Gospel: Reviews, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Book: Religious Ferment in Russia: Correspondence Pertaining to Domestic Publication, 1966-1972 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Book: Religious Ferment in Russia: Correspondence Pertaining to Foreign Publication, 1967-1972 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Book: Religious Ferment in Russia: Correspondence Pertaining to Research, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Book: Religious Ferment in Russia: Reviews (1 of2), 1967-1968 March (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Book: Religious Ferment in Russia: Reviews (2 of 2), 1968 April-1971, undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Book: Religious Ferment in Russia: Reviews: Correspondence, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Book: Religious Ferment in Russia: Review Lists, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Book: Religious Ferment in Russia: Financial Documents and Promotional Materials, 1968, undated (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Book: Young Christians in Russia: Correspondence Pertaining to Publication, 1973-1976 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Book: Young Christians in Russia: Draft Manuscript, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Book: Young Christians in Russia: Revised Manuscript, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Book: Young Christians in Russia: Uncorrected Proof, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Book: Young Christians in Russia: Reviews, 1973-1978 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Book: Minority Rights Group Report "Religious Minorities in the Soviet Union 1960-70": Reviews, 1970-1975, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Book: The Church in Danger: Correspondence Pertaining to Publication, 1965-1970 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Book: The Church in Danger: Introduction: Manuscript, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Book: The Church in Danger: Chapter "Reflections on the Dialogue": Manuscript, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Book: The Church in Danger: Chapter "The Religious Situation in Poland" by Xenia Howard-Johnston: Manuscript, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Book: The Church in Danger: Chapter "The Church in Israel" by Peter Pavey: Manuscript, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Book: The Church in Danger: Chapter "The Church in the Sudan" by Jolf de Saram: Manuscript, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Book: The Church in Danger: Chapter "Turkey" by Wilfrid T.F. Castle: Manuscript, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Book: Documents on Modern Russian Church History: Memorandum of Agreement with Publisher, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Book: Religious Liberty in the Soviet Union: Published Report Summary and Reviews, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Book: Religious Liberty in the Soviet Union: Minutes of Editorial Committee Meeting, 1976 March 16 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Book: Christian Prisoners in the USSR: Keston College Staff Study: Draft Manuscript, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Book: Christian Prisoners in the USSR: Keston College Staff Study: Reviews, 1977-1985 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Book: Risen Indeed: Lessons in Faith from the Soviet Union: Manuscript "Holy Russia": Draft 1, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Book: Risen Indeed: Lessons in Faith from the Soviet Union: Manuscript "Holy Russia": Draft 2, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Book: Risen Indeed: Lessons in Faith from the Soviet Union: Manuscript "Holy Russia": Draft 3, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Book: Risen Indeed: Lessons in Faith from the Soviet Union: Published copy with notes, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 4)